<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Englands vvelcome to Iames by the grace of God, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. Wherein is shewed her zealous loue, and reuerent dutie to her soueraigne. Composed into three cantoes.</title>
            <title>Englands welcome to James.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1603</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04311</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 14422</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S109121</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99844771</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99844771</idno>
            <idno type="VID">3504</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04311)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 3504)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1313:12a)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Englands vvelcome to Iames by the grace of God, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. Wherein is shewed her zealous loue, and reuerent dutie to her soueraigne. Composed into three cantoes.</title>
                  <title>Englands welcome to James.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[26] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for E.VV. and C.K.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1603.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴ D²  (-D2).</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Englands welcome to King Iames.</note>
                  <note>STC 14362.5 bound in following quire A.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
                  <note>With: The copie of the K. Maiesties letter to the l. maior of the citie of London, and to the aldermen and commons of the same. [London : R. Barker, 1603].</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  I, --  King of England, 1566-1625 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-10</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:1"/>
            <p>Englands vvelcome TO <hi>Iames</hi> by the grace of God, King of England, Scotland, France and Ireland, defender of the faith, &amp;c. Wherein is ſhewed her zealous loue, and reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent dutie to her Soueraigne. Compoſed into three Cantoes.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for E.VV. and C.K. 1603.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:2"/>
            <head>The Authors encouragement not to be diſcomforted for the follie of euery finde-fault.</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>F men may credit auncient writs,</l>
               <l>or nouels great of fame,</l>
               <l>Or wander ſafelie through the ſtraites,</l>
               <l>where Wiſedome winnes her name:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or if deedes done in former daies,</l>
               <l>may haue ſome freſh attyre:</l>
               <l>To make the Reader arme himſelfe,</l>
               <l>a new with freſh deſire:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or if that Poets pennes, may winne</l>
               <l>ſuch profit for their paine,</l>
               <l>As elder daies did gladlie yeeld,</l>
               <l>as guerdon for their gaine,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Or if that praiſes ſpoke in right,</l>
               <l>and glorie of a King:</l>
               <l>Vnto the Author breed no ſpight,</l>
               <l>but true aeternizing:</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Then haue I hit the white</l>
               <l>where-at ten thouſand ſhoote:</l>
               <l>If acceptance be the leaues,</l>
               <l>and gratitude the roote.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>For why ſuch Daſtards as doe doubt,</l>
               <l>the noyſe of ratling Drum:</l>
               <l>By my conſent ſhall neuer be,</l>
               <l>prefer'd to Captaines roome.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>For he that doubts annoy,</l>
               <l>before his ſute begin:</l>
               <l>May lump in bogue with countrie Kate,</l>
               <l>when ventrous Ladies win.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So he that ſpares the poole to lade,</l>
               <l>can hardly come by fiſh:</l>
               <l>Nor he that ſtill conceales his griefe,</l>
               <l>can euer win his wiſh.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor yet the Meacocks minde,</l>
               <l>that's drownde in ſelfe conceit,</l>
               <l>Can euer ſcale <hi>Pernaſſus</hi> Tops,</l>
               <l>although the pathe be ſtraight.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So he that feares the frumpe,</l>
               <l>of euery leſting ſwaine:</l>
               <l>Conceales the pride of natures gifts,</l>
               <l>and ſpends his time in vaine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Each writer muſt be arm'd,</l>
               <l>to beare and brooke a ſcoffe:</l>
               <l>And as it is by follie giuen,</l>
               <l>with wiſdome ſhake it off.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Diſpaire not for a ſcorne,</l>
               <l>leane ſtill on patience ſtaffe:</l>
               <l>For <hi>Pallas</hi> clearkes are ſifted out,</l>
               <l>as Corne is from the Chaffe.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:3"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Striue thou with all thy ſtrength,</l>
               <l>the golden meane to keepe:</l>
               <l>Pleaſe thou the good, and let the reſt</l>
               <l>in ſcorners ſaddle ſleepe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Let all the raſh rewardes,</l>
               <l>not make thee ill apaide,</l>
               <l>Thy worke ſhall keepe thy fame aliue,</l>
               <l>when they full lowe are laide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>And children yet vnborne,</l>
               <l>ſhall deſcant on thy deeds,</l>
               <l>With treble bleſſings to the ground,</l>
               <l>that bare ſuch happie ſeeds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Grudge not to looſe an inch,</l>
               <l>ſo thou maiſt gaine an ell:</l>
               <l>Feare not at all the fooles reproofe,</l>
               <l>if wiſe-men like thee well.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thou muſt be bought and ſolde,</l>
               <l>by difference of delights:</l>
               <l>Some laude the life of bloudy <hi>Mars,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>ſome reuerence carpet Knights.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Some honor loue, ſome loath her lawe,</l>
               <l>ſome muſicke doe eſteeme:</l>
               <l>Some hunt, ſome hauke, with ſeuerall ſports</l>
               <l>ſuch as they deereſt deeme.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Giue euery man his ſcope,</l>
               <l>to loue what he likes beſt:</l>
               <l>Weake is the worke that willing mindes</l>
               <l>make not a welcome gueſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:4"/>
            <lg>
               <l>Leaue off thy hope to pleaſe,</l>
               <l>both Court and countrie too;</l>
               <l>Or elſe thou tak'ſt in hand a worke,</l>
               <l>that Chriſt could neuer doe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Driue from thy ſtudie ſlouth,</l>
               <l>with paine be buſie ſtill:</l>
               <l>So ſhall thy wants be all excuſ'd,</l>
               <l>and guarded with good wil.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="epitaph">
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:4"/>
            <head>An Epitaph vpon the death of our late Soueraigne Ladie, of famous memory Queene <hi>Elizableth.</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <l>ALL dames that euer tryumpht in ioy,</l>
               <l>With ſorrowfull hearts come waile ye.</l>
               <l>Your pleaſant Songs may turne to ſobbet,</l>
               <l>No ſighings can preuaile yee:</l>
               <l>A Diamond flower of late ye loſt,</l>
               <l>Whoſe loyall heart was kept with coſt,</l>
               <l>For euer let fame her name goe boaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Shee makes me ſigh when I ſhould ſleepe,</l>
               <l>With blubberd teares lamenting,</l>
               <l>No earthly ioy can profer'd be,</l>
               <l>To my poore hearts contenting:</l>
               <l>But ſtill, and ſtill in ſorrow I ſay,</l>
               <l>A precious pearle is turn'd to clay,</l>
               <l>Whoſe vertues flooriſht as flower in may.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This wretched life compar'd may be,</l>
               <l>Vnto the flowers ſpringing,</l>
               <l>Or to the bird on loftie buſh,</l>
               <l>That ſurged notes is ſinging:</l>
               <l>Yet in the minute of an houre.</l>
               <l>The fowler doth her breath deuour,</l>
               <l>And life retaines no longer power.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The fragrants flower that euer did grow,</l>
               <l>The beauty will be fleeting,</l>
               <l>The braueſt branch that euer did blow,</l>
               <l>With Sythe ſometime is meeting:</l>
               <l>The ſtouteſt heart that ere was borne,</l>
               <l>Hath been diſgrac't and left forlorne,</l>
               <l>Death holdes all golden giftes in ſcorne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>What though her mortall ſhape be gone?</l>
               <l>Her memorie reſtes behinde her:</l>
               <l>Deſeruing praiſe of worthy dames,</l>
               <l>That many a day will minde her.</l>
               <l>Then though her corpes be ſhrin'd in clay,</l>
               <l>And death hath reſt her hence away,</l>
               <l>Her noble fame ſhall liue for aye.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Virtutie excepta, concedunt omnia fato.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="acrostic">
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:5"/>
            <head>God ſaue</head>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> In memorable braſse let there be writ</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> An euerlaſting ſtorie of a King:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>M</hi> Maruell of men! wonder of chiefeſt wit!</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi> Eternall glorie doth to England bring.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>S</hi> So let his ſtile be fram'd, and he be ſaid,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi> Englands true King, ſucceſſor of a Maide.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>K</hi> Know forraigne powers: Englands true loyaltie,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I</hi> Is bent in ſeruice to her Soueraigne King:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi> Nor ſhal the fierce allar'ms, nor frowne of enemy</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>G</hi> Giue alteration, or daunted courage bring.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>O</hi> O no, ſhe ſhall, firſt in a ſcarlet flood,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>F</hi> Fight to the lips, with loſse of deareſt blood.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi> Euen as the day which firſt proclaim'd his name,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi> Neuer as yet did ſeeme to make an end:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>G</hi> Glorious with bon-fires pyl'd on ſtatelieſt frame,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>L</hi> Lookt like the morning, the Sun, the night: which did pretend</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A</hi> A quiet raigne, &amp; happy to our King;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>N</hi> Neare ceaſing Ioyes and his aeternizing.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>D</hi> Do therefore England, marching in ſtately traines,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>E</hi> Englands true Leige-lord, welcome bid (King <hi>Iames.</hi>)</l>
            </lg>
            <closer>God ſaue King <hi>James.</hi>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:3504:5"/>
            <head>THE COPIE OF the K. Maieſties letter to the L. Maior of the Citie of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don, and to the Aldermen and Commons of the ſame.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Ruſtie and welbelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued,</hi> Wee greete you heartily well. Being informed of your great forwardneſſe in that iust and Honourable action of proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming vs your Soueraigne Lord and King, immediatly after the deceaſe of our late dearest ſister the <hi>Queene,</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:3504:6"/> wherein you haue giuen a ſingular good proofe of your ancient fidelitie (a repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation hereditarie to that our Citie of <hi>London,</hi> beeing the Chamber of our Jmperiall Crowne, and euer free from all ſhadowes of tumultuous and vnlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full courſes:) We could not omit with all the ſpeed wee might poſsible, to giue you hereby a taste of our thankefull minde for the ſame: And withall, aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance that you cannot craue any thing of vs fit for the maintenance of you all in generall, and euery one of you in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler, but it ſhalbe most willingly per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by vs, whoſe ſpeciall care ſhall euer be to prouide for the continuance and increaſe of your preſent happines: Deſiring you in the meane time to goe constantly forward in doing all and whatſoeuer things you ſhall finde ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:3504:6"/> or expedient for the good go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uernment of our ſaid Citie in execution of Justice, as you haue bene in vſe to doe in our ſaid dearest Sisters time, till our pleaſure be further knowen vnto you.</p>
            <p>Thus not doubting but you will do as ye may be fully aſsured of our gracious fauour towards you in the highest de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree, we bid you heartily farewell.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Halirudhouſe <date>the 28. of March. 1603.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Iames R.</signed>
            </closer>
            <trailer>To our trustie and welbeloued <hi>Robert Lee</hi> L. Maior of our Citie of <hi>London,</hi> and to our welbeloued the Aldermen and Commons of the ſame.</trailer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:7"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:7"/>
            <head>Englands vvelcome TO <hi>Iames</hi> by the grace of God, King of England, Scotland, France and Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, defender of the faith, &amp;c.</head>
            <div n="1" type="canto">
               <head>Canto. 1.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>EVen as a widdow hauing loſt her ſpouſe,</l>
                  <l>Doth cloſe her mourning thoughts in ſable hew,</l>
                  <l>So was't with me when I loſt my repoſe,</l>
                  <l>My ſole defendreſſe hauing bid adew;</l>
                  <l>My adamantine rocke, which was ſo true.</l>
                  <l>For like a widdow mourning for her mate,</l>
                  <l>I hung my head, my trembling ſence did ſhake.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I was affraide, yet knew not what to feare,</l>
                  <l>A chilling tremor did poſſeſſe my bones;</l>
                  <l>I l ſtned ſtill, yet ſtill I naught could heare,</l>
                  <l>Which did augment my mourning and my mones,</l>
                  <l>And made me ſigh with many ſorrowing grones.</l>
                  <l>Muſing vpon my ſtate, I heard one ſing,</l>
                  <l>Cheare vp thy heart, for thou ſhalt haue a King.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:8"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>This vnexpected voice pierc'd through my eares,</l>
                  <l>And made a paſſage to my ſorrowing hart:</l>
                  <l>Where it was mourning, circumcinct with feares,</l>
                  <l>Lamenting wofullie his maiſters ſmart,</l>
                  <l>As one being ſmitten with a poyſoned Dart.</l>
                  <l>The voice amaz'd it, it gaz'd on the voice,</l>
                  <l>The voice ſpake thus, and bid my heart reioyce.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What though thy Prince, haue had a proſperous raigne,</l>
                  <l>Thou muſt not thinke for euer t'enioy one Prince:</l>
                  <l>What though in peace, ſhe did thee long maintaine,</l>
                  <l>(Peace-giuing God can giue an other Prince,</l>
                  <l>And he ſhall be a Noble vertuous Prince,</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall in wealth, in loue, in truth, and peace,</l>
                  <l>Encreaſe thy ioyes, encreaſing ſtill, increaſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Long maiſt thou Ioy, and he a Prince may be,</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Scepter ſwayes the glory of thy land:</l>
                  <l>Whoſe Sun-like beames, <hi>Europe</hi> ſhall ſhining ſee,</l>
                  <l>Vpholding Englands good with happie hand,</l>
                  <l>Glorious adornment, of thy peacefull land;</l>
                  <l>His ſtates moſt ſtate-like each in his degree,</l>
                  <l>Shall grac'd be by his gracious Maieſtie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>And he himſelfe, grac'd by the Gods aboue,</l>
                  <l>With learning by (<hi>Ioues</hi> of ſpring richly dight:)</l>
                  <l>His minde hath beautified, with wiſdomes loue,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>las</hi> endu'd him: <hi>Joue</hi> whome all men dread,</l>
                  <l>(As all men ought that mighty King to dread.)</l>
                  <l>All other graces which could wiſhed be,</l>
                  <l>Hath dew'd in plenty on his maieſty.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:8"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Ceaſe to lament encounter griefe with ioy,</l>
                  <l>And thou ſhalt quickely haue the vpper hand:</l>
                  <l>Ioy in thy King and thinke it is a ioy,</l>
                  <l>To haue a vertuous Prince gouerne thy land:</l>
                  <l>Which ſhall againſt all forraine foes withſtand:</l>
                  <l>This hauing ſaid quite vaniſht was the voyce,</l>
                  <l>I rouz'd me vp my heart begun t'reioyce.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Yet ſtill I ſtai'd, and feard it was a dreame,</l>
                  <l>Me thought it was too pleaſing to be true:</l>
                  <l>I look't about, (as gazing on a ſtreame,</l>
                  <l>Ones eyes are dazled with the ſliding view,</l>
                  <l>Seeing the water heere, was there but new)</l>
                  <l>So were my eyes, I naught diſtinct could ſee:</l>
                  <l>My eyes were in my minde, minde in my eye.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Long had I not thus look't with mixed dint,</l>
                  <l>When loe, I ſaw faſt fixed on a poaſt</l>
                  <l>A long broade ſcroule, in Proclamation print,</l>
                  <l>And Nobles names vpon it were imboſt,</l>
                  <l>Which did adorne the paper, it the poaſt,</l>
                  <l>I ſtarted vp thinking to reade the names:</l>
                  <l>When vnderneath I ſaw, <hi>God ſaue King James.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>I trembling ſtood, as one was ſtill in feare,</l>
                  <l>I gaz'd about as one was ſtill amaz'd:</l>
                  <l>Vntill a wel-tun'd concord I might heare,</l>
                  <l>With one conſent and ſtill one name they praiſ'd,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill made me in feare, which was amaz'd.</l>
                  <l>I drew me neere to heare what they did ſing,</l>
                  <l>I heard them ſing King <hi>Iames,</hi> God ſaue our King.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:9"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then as the widdow I reioyc't a freſh,</l>
                  <l>And quite forgot the ſorrow I was in:</l>
                  <l>When ſhe is tempt with frailty of the fleſh,</l>
                  <l>To take new husband, new Ioyes to begin,</l>
                  <l>And hauing taine him being trick and trim,</l>
                  <l>As ſhe is gladſome on her wedding day,</l>
                  <l>So I reioyc't hearing them thus to ſay.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No ſooner had I with mind-caſting counts,</l>
                  <l>Ponder'd his title, and his true deſcent,</l>
                  <l>His Noble vertues, each other to ſurmount:</l>
                  <l>In high'ſt degree, in ſtriuing conflict bent,</l>
                  <l>His gratious wiſdome and his gouernment.</l>
                  <l>But as the Sun enſeweth ſtill the raine,</l>
                  <l>My heart did leape and ſo reioyc't againe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>No ſooner had my of-ſpring heard t'was true,</l>
                  <l>It had pleaſ'd God giue them a gratious King,</l>
                  <l>When each in pompe, and each in publike view,</l>
                  <l>His royall name which did this comfort bring:</l>
                  <l>With one aſſent concordingly did ſing,</l>
                  <l>My greater powers in ſtate, which ſtate proclaimes,</l>
                  <l>With caps vp throwne, <hi>God ſaue our King, King James.</hi>
                  </l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus loue and duety tooke each others parts,</l>
                  <l>They ſhew'd their duetie in obedience,</l>
                  <l>Loue ſhew'd it elfe within th ir ioyful hearts,</l>
                  <l>(As when in loue, with a ſelfe feeling ſence,</l>
                  <l>The Louer giues his loue preheminence.)</l>
                  <l>So did my people ioyfullie reioyce:</l>
                  <l>Lauding their King with one concording voice.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:9"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>The little birds proude of this vnitie,</l>
                  <l>Begun to tune their chirping ſiluer'd notes,</l>
                  <l>The lofty trees glad of their harmonie,</l>
                  <l>Did entertaine them in their new greene coats,</l>
                  <l>Sending foorth muſicke from melodious throats,</l>
                  <l>The tree's adorn'd the birds, the birds the trees,</l>
                  <l>Who flockt into them (as a ſwarme of Bees.)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Which lately hauing left their wonted hiue,</l>
                  <l>Partly for noueltie, and parte for loue:</l>
                  <l>For loue, to let the little yonglings thriue:</l>
                  <l>(Which doth in Bees a kindely nature prooue)</l>
                  <l>Themſelues into ſome other place remooue.</l>
                  <l>Where on ſome buſhe, or clagging on ſome tree,</l>
                  <l>They doe remaine, till they new hyued bee.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>As flew the Bees in ſwarmes, ſo did the birds,</l>
                  <l>For they came flocking to thee (all haile ſing trees)</l>
                  <l>As flee the Bees, their hiue, ſo did the birds,</l>
                  <l>They left the eaſings, when paſt were colde degrees</l>
                  <l>Of ſnowy winter, and congealed freeze.</l>
                  <l>And ſinging ſet in trees, <hi>welcome thou ſpring:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>The ſpringing happines of</hi> (Iames <hi>our King.</hi>)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Like trees, and Birds, ſo did Dame <hi>Tellus</hi> too,</l>
                  <l>For ſhe put on her naturall ornaments,</l>
                  <l>As when her louer comes her for to wooe:</l>
                  <l>She decks her ſelfe in richeſt complements:</l>
                  <l>And doth perfume her breath with ſweeteſt ſents,</l>
                  <l>So did ſhe now, for this was in the ſpring,</l>
                  <l>And in her pride ſhe went to meete our King.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:10"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>I gladſome was to ſee her loyall roabe,</l>
                  <l>Her ſpangled garments, and her light-ſome cheare;</l>
                  <l>(As in a froſtie night, within the globe</l>
                  <l>A glorious ſight of bright-ſome ſtarres appeare,</l>
                  <l>Who with their twinckling ſtemme now there, now here:</l>
                  <l>So was her kirtle all imbrodring ſet,</l>
                  <l>Heere, with a primroſe: there, a violet.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Her other ornaments be ſuited this,</l>
                  <l>For ſhe was Prince-like in her chiefeſt prime;</l>
                  <l>Her ſweet perfumes ſhe ſtill did ſeeme to kiſſe,</l>
                  <l>As being glad they in ſo fit a time</l>
                  <l>Came to adorne her; that in pompe and prime,</l>
                  <l>With her delights, ſhe might new pleaſures bring,</l>
                  <l>And be a ioyance to (<hi>King</hi> Iames <hi>our King.</hi>)</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The modeſt Muſes tended on her grace,</l>
                  <l>The Graces round about her ſeem'd to ſing;</l>
                  <l>The frisking Fayries daunc'd their rounds apace,</l>
                  <l>The melodie was ſuch the place did ring:</l>
                  <l>Their Song they ſung was ſtill <hi>(God ſaue the King.)</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Amongſt the reſt, I gladdeſt of the reſt,</l>
                  <l>Tun'd vp my Lute, and ſung amongſt the beſt.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:10"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="sonnet">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Sonnet.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>LEt <hi>Phoebus</hi> in his brighteſt rayes.</l>
                        <l>Tune vp <hi>Appollos voice,</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>Let mortals in theſe happie daies</l>
                        <l>With gladſome hearts reioyce:</l>
                        <l>With one conſent let vs all ſay,</l>
                        <l>Of late there hap't a happie day;</l>
                        <l>Therefore reioyce, reioyce therefore, reioyce &amp; ſing,</l>
                        <l>For it hath pleaſ'd God to giue vs a King.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let all the true and noble hearts,</l>
                        <l>Wherewith England abounds:</l>
                        <l>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nto their King, of rareſt parts,</l>
                        <l>Be loyall ſubiects found.</l>
                        <l>Sing they melodious harmony,</l>
                        <l>Sing welcome, welcome hartily,</l>
                        <l>Therefore reioyce, reioyce therefore, reioyce and ſing,</l>
                        <l>For it hath pleaſ'd God to giue vs a King.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="canto">
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:11"/>
               <head>The ſecond Canto.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>AS I was ſinging thus with cheerefull voice,</l>
                  <l>The Anticke voice appeares, which earſt appear'd,</l>
                  <l>England, quoth ſhe, ſeeing thou haſt chiefeſt choyce</l>
                  <l>Of true Nobilitie and gallant Peeres,</l>
                  <l>Why doſt forget to recompence their cares;</l>
                  <l>Who with their wiſedome and their pollicie,</l>
                  <l>Kept thee in peace, being in miſerie.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>If that their wiſedomes had not well fore-ſeene,</l>
                  <l>Thy dangers eminent being in diſtreſſe,</l>
                  <l>When thou hadſt loſt thy lateſt Soueraigne Queene;</l>
                  <l>Plunging in woe, wayling in wretchedneſſe,</l>
                  <l>Lamenting ſtill thy late loſt Gouerneſſe:</l>
                  <l>Thou mightſt haue falne to ſome ſeditious hand,</l>
                  <l>Which would haue rac'd thy name and ſpoil'd thy land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Perhaps thou may'ſt thus fooliſhly reply,</l>
                  <l>(They knew my King had right and tytle good:)</l>
                  <l>Therefore I might liue in ſecuritie,</l>
                  <l>Seeing that there was no feare of ſhedding blood;</l>
                  <l>The way to his ſucceſſion plainly ſtood.</l>
                  <l>If thou ſayſt thus, thou proou'ſt thy ſelfe vnwiſe,</l>
                  <l>For he that hath leaſt right will ſooneſt riſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>For he whoſe tytle is direct and plaine,</l>
                  <l>And needes no varniſhing to ſet it out;</l>
                  <l>And hath a ſpotleſſe minde, free from diſdaine,</l>
                  <l>And liues ſecure, not hauing cauſe to doubt,</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3504:11"/>
                  <l>And feares no feare-full foes, nor raſcall route;</l>
                  <l>He ſooneſt is deceiu'd, and ſooneſt harm'd:</l>
                  <l>For being ſet on, he is found vnarm'd.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When as the proude, ſet in ambitious throane,</l>
                  <l>Which by vnſurping haue obtain'd a crowne:</l>
                  <l>Are ſtill in feare, neuer are left alone,</l>
                  <l>But are perſu'd with dangers vp and downe,</l>
                  <l>Byting their lips for anger, then they frowne;</l>
                  <l>Bending their browes, thinking't a helliſh thing,</l>
                  <l>They cannot liue as ſafe, as lawfull King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>But theſe I ſay like to a watchfull ſnake,</l>
                  <l>Neuer dare ſleepe but with one open eye:</l>
                  <l>For euery doubt, doth make their ſences quake,</l>
                  <l>And feare doth force them oft t'vſe crueltie,</l>
                  <l>And ſtill perſeuer in their tyranie.</l>
                  <l>For euery bud which may but danger bring,</l>
                  <l>They nip it off when't is in tender ſpring.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thus feare at al times, armed is with force,</l>
                  <l>When ſweet ſecurity, is ſtill vnarm'd,</l>
                  <l>And tyrants ſeldome euer brooke remorſe,</l>
                  <l>When they may gaine by others that are harm'd,</l>
                  <l>They care not who be colde, ſo they be warm'd.</l>
                  <l>And therefore England thou haſt cauſe to grace,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe Noble Peeres, which did this feare deface.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>She hauing ſaid, I look't, and turn'd me round,</l>
                  <l>When preſently the voyce that ſpoke was gone:</l>
                  <l>I cal'd a Iury, and I guilty found</l>
                  <l>My ſelfe: which careleſly had left vndone,</l>
                  <l>Thoſe worthy praiſes, which I ought t'haue done.</l>
                  <pb facs="tcp:3504:12"/>
                  <l>Vnto thoſe worthyes, which proclaim'd my King:</l>
                  <l>Then tooke my Lute, and thus againe did ſing.</l>
               </lg>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="sonnet">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Sonnet.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>ALL thoſe which late were wrapt in woe,</l>
                        <l>With ioyfull hearts let them come ſing:</l>
                        <l>Their paſſed griefe, and care let goe,</l>
                        <l>Let them reioyce they haue a King.</l>
                        <l>Let them ſay with one ioyfull heart,</l>
                        <l>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ertue, and wiſedome ſhines in Court.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let them giue praiſes to our Peeres,</l>
                        <l>Which thus haue ſow'd their wiſedomes skill:</l>
                        <l>Which haue abandon'd gaſtly feares,</l>
                        <l>And fram'd each thing euen to our will.</l>
                        <l>Let them J ſay with ioy and mirth,</l>
                        <l>Be gladſome of bright wiſedomes birth.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let them giue praiſe to pollicie,</l>
                        <l>Which did fore-caſt what ſhould betide:</l>
                        <l>And let them in their iollicie,</l>
                        <l>And in the prime of all their pride,</l>
                        <l>Giue chiefeſt praiſe to chiefeſt wit,</l>
                        <l>Let them annex iudgement to it.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Let them giue praiſe vnto the olde,</l>
                        <l>Whoſe grand experience makes them graue:</l>
                        <l>Whoſe noble vertues ſhine like golde,</l>
                        <l>Or ſparkling Diamond gliſtring braue.</l>
                        <l>Let this be ſung ſans flatterie,</l>
                        <l>For't longs to our Nobilitie.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:12"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Long had I not thus praiſ'd my happie ſtate,</l>
                  <l>When I was interrupted once againe;</l>
                  <l>I then grew angrie, curſing cruell fate,</l>
                  <l>Which would not let me make my pleaſures plaine,</l>
                  <l>I lookt about with furious diſdaine.</l>
                  <l>When I behelde (the voice) in angry wiſe,</l>
                  <l>Which crying ſaid England thou art not wiſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Thou art as brutiſh now as beaſtly ſwine,</l>
                  <l>Which vnder the broad Beech eates vp her maſt:</l>
                  <l>Yet to the top their eyes doe neu'r incline,</l>
                  <l>Looking from whence it falles; they eate ſo faſt;</l>
                  <l>This ſimilye before my eyes ſhe caſt.</l>
                  <l>England (ſaith ſhe) giue but attentiue eare,</l>
                  <l>And in an other tune thou ſhalt me heare.</l>
               </lg>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="canto">
               <head>The third Canto in a differing verſe.</head>
               <lg>
                  <l>THen graſping hard my conſcience by the hand,</l>
                  <l>England (quoth ſhe) tho'art now in happie caſe:</l>
                  <l>Thou haſt a vertuous King t'gouerne thy land,</l>
                  <l>And graueſt wiſedome flowes in euerie place.</l>
                  <l>Thou doſt reioyce and to them praiſes ſing,</l>
                  <l>Yet doſt forget the giuer of thy King.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Gods Sonne, his fathers glorious ſhine, who raignes</l>
                  <l>In ſtatelie throne, earthes prop, heauens mightie ſtay;</l>
                  <l>Whome furies feare, and deuils in dragging chaines,</l>
                  <l>Whome men, and beaſtes, and Angels bright obay.</l>
                  <l>Twiſe borne, who as a Gyant tooke his race,</l>
                  <l>From heauen; was borne for thee, in ſtable baſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>He laide in cribbe new borne, thy ſtate lamented,</l>
                  <l>He wept for thee, yfram'd of lumpiſh clay;</l>
                  <l>His head, which earth and haughtie heauen inuented,</l>
                  <l>In ſtable vile on ſtonie pillow lay.</l>
                  <l>Thy King, heauens Queene, in homelie cloutes did holde,</l>
                  <l>Not wrapt in roabes be-wrought with wouen golde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>According to the law the Octane day,</l>
                  <l>His tender fleſh with knife of ſtone was ſhred:</l>
                  <l>The auncient ryte, he would not diſobay;</l>
                  <l>For thee with paine his purple bloud was ſhed.</l>
                  <l>He death of death, and conquerour of ſinne,</l>
                  <l>Thy ſauing health at firſt did thus beginne.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Through tyrants rage he could not reſt in manger,</l>
                  <l>Ambition powred out a bloudie ſhower;</l>
                  <l>He fled through deſarts wilde, a wandring ſtranger,</l>
                  <l>Exylde to <hi>Aegipt</hi> in his tender flower,</l>
                  <l>From cribbe to caue he toyl'd to <hi>Nilus</hi> ſtrand,</l>
                  <l>And thence with paine reiourn'd to <hi>Iewiſh</hi> land.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What did he heere? his parents he obayes;</l>
                  <l>He wept for thee, he watched night and day:</l>
                  <l>With eyes and hands to heauen vp-throwne he prayes</l>
                  <l>He ſought no pompe, no reſt, no earthlie ſway.</l>
                  <l>His light, his life, his deedes did others teach,</l>
                  <l>Vntill ſuch time as he muſt goe to preach.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:13"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Where is his home? where is a place of reſt</l>
                  <l>Repoſ'd for him wherein to lay his head?</l>
                  <l>The little bird can frame a quiet neſt,</l>
                  <l>The wylie Fox can haunt a reſting ſtead.</l>
                  <l>From cribbe to croſſe, whiles breath in him remaines,</l>
                  <l>He found no reſt, but trouble, toyle and paines.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This King, thy prieſt, and Prince of happie peace,</l>
                  <l>Through <hi>Iewries</hi> land did trauell too and fro:</l>
                  <l>To cure both ſicke and ſore, he did not ceaſe,</l>
                  <l>No raging ſtorme could hinder him to go.</l>
                  <l>Where he might worke his fathers worthy will,</l>
                  <l>And with lifes foode might ſoule and body fill.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>An Angels trumpe from heauen proclaim'd his name</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Ieſus,</hi> who came loſt <hi>Adams</hi> impes to ſaue;</l>
                  <l>Whoſe wondrous actes deſerues eternall fame,</l>
                  <l>He <hi>Lazarus</hi> reuiued from the graue.</l>
                  <l>Whoſe ſtincking coarſe, and rotten carkas colde,</l>
                  <l>Foure daies and nights was couered in the molde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>What ſhall I ſpeake of other dead, reuiued?</l>
                  <l>Or make rehearſall of ſuch obiects ſere?</l>
                  <l>Of blind and lame, of ſence and ſight depriued,</l>
                  <l>He made the dumbe to ſpeake, and deafe to heare.</l>
                  <l>He, fowle infected ſoules from ſinne did cure,</l>
                  <l>And vgly vlcer'd Leapers clenſed pure.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When waltring waues, and windes would ouerthrow,</l>
                  <l>The ſhaking ſhips amid the Seas ytoſt:</l>
                  <l>He cauſ'd the ſturdie ſtormes to ſtoope below,</l>
                  <l>And ſaued ſhips and men like to be loſt.</l>
                  <l>He made the lame, in leaping beare his bed,</l>
                  <l>And with fiue loaues, two fiſh, fiue thouſand fed.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:14"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>He, water wan conuerted into wine,</l>
                  <l>He daunted deuills, and furies put to flight,</l>
                  <l>He for thy ſake did let them ſtrangle ſwine,</l>
                  <l>He taught all ſorts of men to follow light.</l>
                  <l>His workes within no leaues can be enroul'd,</l>
                  <l>The ample world his wonders cannot hould.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Doe what he could, his actions did diſpleaſe,</l>
                  <l>His worthy words incurred ſpotleſſe blame:</l>
                  <l>No Angell tongue their malice could appeaſe,</l>
                  <l>They forged crymes, and fained lyes did frame.</l>
                  <l>They mercileſſe will kill their louing King,</l>
                  <l>Who came to ſhrow'd them vnder mercies wing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Loſt childe, hells ſlaue, Deuils gueſt, did him betray,</l>
                  <l>For thee, that Lambe was traterouſly ſolde:</l>
                  <l>The <hi>Ethniſh</hi> doggs, and Iewes haule him away,</l>
                  <l>They whip him bound vnto a piller colde.</l>
                  <l>The mightie maule of death, diuell, hell and ſinne,</l>
                  <l>By coined lyes, is falſelie compaſt in.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>His fathers wiſedome, diuine truth is taken,</l>
                  <l>God and man, heauens lamp and glorious light,</l>
                  <l>Is of his owne deciples deare forſaken,</l>
                  <l>Is bound and led away as theefe by night,</l>
                  <l>He whipped is and beat, till from the crowne,</l>
                  <l>Tot'h ground red ſtreames of blood diſtilled downe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Stout <hi>Gedons</hi> Trumpets kept the dreadfull ſound,</l>
                  <l>His brickle Lanthornes broken, ſhined bright:</l>
                  <l>But Chriſt his trumpe lay ſmothered in the ground,</l>
                  <l>The lamps of light and truth did lacke their light.</l>
                  <l>When Iewes their Maiſter bound away had led,</l>
                  <l>Th'Apoſtles into hollowe caues are fled.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:14"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>Now Peters lofty vants and braggs are knowne,</l>
                  <l>That mightie mount is rent and ſhaken ſunder:</l>
                  <l>A maidens voice the fact hath ouerthrowne,</l>
                  <l>A Cocks third cry proclaimes the rocke brought vnder.</l>
                  <l>That ſiluer bell hath loſt it ſounding tung,</l>
                  <l>Which all abroad with praiſe the Goſpell rung.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The Lambe of God to Pilats hall is brought,</l>
                  <l>His dome and iudgement, moſt vniuſt to haue:</l>
                  <l>Where fraud and falſe ſurmiſing witnes ſought,</l>
                  <l>His worthy words by wreſting to depraue.</l>
                  <l>They ſpit through ſpighte vpon his gracious face,</l>
                  <l>And they with blowes and buffets him diſgrace.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When Diuels, hell ſnakes, foule fends and furyes fell,</l>
                  <l>Had fil'd blaſphemous Iewes with poyſon rancke,</l>
                  <l>Then they with ſpight, contempt and malice ſwell,</l>
                  <l>Within their hearts miſcheuous vennome ſancke.</l>
                  <l>They ſound theſe bloody words in Pilats hall,</l>
                  <l>We craue, naile him on croſſe before vs all.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They ſcoffe at him and laugh him vnto ſcorne,</l>
                  <l>And him as King in purple roabe array,</l>
                  <l>They ſpit, they ſpight and crowne his head with thorne,</l>
                  <l>In ieſting wiſe on knees all hayle they ſay,</l>
                  <l>They force him alſo beare a heauie croſſe,</l>
                  <l>Tot'h place where he redeemed Adams loſſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>They hoyſe him vp vpon a filthie mount,</l>
                  <l>On croſſe both hand and foote they fixed ſure:</l>
                  <l>Betwixt two theeues whoſe worſe they him account,</l>
                  <l>Where he moſt bitter torments did endure,</l>
                  <l>If all the Martirs paines were put in one,</l>
                  <l>They all to this ſhould be eſteemed none.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:15"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>He thirſting on the croſſe mans ſoule to ſaue,</l>
                  <l>Did fainting ſeeme, to them for drinke to call:</l>
                  <l>They dreaming that indeed he drinke would haue,</l>
                  <l>In place thereof did proffer bitter gall.</l>
                  <l>Thus ſeru'd they him, who ſuffered for thy ſake,</l>
                  <l>The Lord of all who heauen and earth did make.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When this was done he yeelded vp the Ghoſt,</l>
                  <l>His ſoule he to his father did commend:</l>
                  <l>He offred vp himſelfe a ſacred hoaſt,</l>
                  <l>And ſo his glorious paſſion made an end.</l>
                  <l>All this he did for thee, yet thou vnkinde,</l>
                  <l>Haſt almoſt rac'd him quite out of thy minde.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>When as the voice ended her long diſcourſe,</l>
                  <l>She gaue me leaue a little for to pauſe:</l>
                  <l>Then hauing ſtood a while, quite out of courſe</l>
                  <l>Was euery thing and I the chiefeſt cauſe.</l>
                  <l>Nature quite out of courſe, to checke my courſe,</l>
                  <l>Neglect her worke, to worke in me remorſe.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then like a childe which hauing done amiſſe,</l>
                  <l>Doth trembling ſtand in feare of Maiſters rod:</l>
                  <l>So did I then: and gladly ſeem'd to kiſſe</l>
                  <l>The very path where I might praiſe my God.</l>
                  <l>And as the childe doth wiſh the deed vndone,</l>
                  <l>So did I wiſh I had with him begun.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>The voice which then did lately ſeeme to chide,</l>
                  <l>Did change her chaunt, and did new comforts bring:</l>
                  <l>Saying oh England thou haſt time and tide,</l>
                  <l>As yet remaining for to praiſe heauens King</l>
                  <l>Take time by'th buſh that growes vpon his brow</l>
                  <l>For that being paſt, thou canſt not take him now.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:15"/>
               <lg>
                  <l>And if thou ſlip'ſt him now, farewell my hope,</l>
                  <l>Thou ſhalt not haue occaſion like to this,</l>
                  <l>Not God knowes when) wherein will be ſuch ſcope,</l>
                  <l>And cauſe of comfort, where nothing is amiſſe.</l>
                  <l>Hauing wiſedomes wealth vertues floriſhing,</l>
                  <l>Which makes thee happy through thy graue wiſe King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Therefore to God, which thus hath been thy ſtay,</l>
                  <l>All honour giue, praiſe him eternally:</l>
                  <l>With hands and heart vp-throwne ſee thou doſt pray,</l>
                  <l>Giue tryple laude vnto his Maieſtie.</l>
                  <l>Giue praiſe to God the giuer of thy King,</l>
                  <l>In glorying him, thou prayſeth ſtill thy King.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>Then ceaſe to praiſe, and pray an other ſpace,</l>
                  <l>That God may graunt him long and happy daies:</l>
                  <l>And proſper all his vertues with his grace,</l>
                  <l>That all the world may teſtifie his praiſe.</l>
                  <l>And that hee'l ſend ſuch wiſedome from aboue,</l>
                  <l>That thou mayſt him in dutie ſerue, hee thee in loue.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>This hauing ſaid, England (ſaid ſhe) adue,</l>
                  <l>Thinke on my words, be ſure when I am gone:</l>
                  <l>Giue God the praiſe, and thou ſhalt neuer rue;</l>
                  <l>For all enſuing dangers comming on,</l>
                  <l>He of his mercie will keepe from thy King,</l>
                  <l>If thou to him doſt onely glorie ſing.</l>
               </lg>
               <lg>
                  <l>With that I heard caeleſtiall harmonie,</l>
                  <l>The voice departed ſtraight into the ayre;</l>
                  <l>To heauen I thinke, for it was heauenlie,</l>
                  <l>Sweet of all ſweets, and fayreſt of all fayre.</l>
                  <l>Then I remembring what the voice had bod,</l>
                  <l>Sung theſe thankeſ-giuings to my liuing God.</l>
               </lg>
               <pb facs="tcp:3504:16"/>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="song">
                  <body>
                     <head>A Song of thankeſ-giuing.</head>
                     <lg>
                        <l>GOds name be glorifyed,</l>
                        <l>who with his heauenly might:</l>
                        <l>Hath hell, in chiefe and top of pride,</l>
                        <l>put to a ſhamefull flight.</l>
                        <l>Who ſent his onely Sonne,</l>
                        <l>mans ſinfull ſoule to ſaue:</l>
                        <l>Which heere on earth a race did run,</l>
                        <l>(to ſinne) a ſeruing ſlaue.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>All glory be to God,</l>
                        <l>which in my widdow-hood:</l>
                        <l>Sent me a husband and a King,</l>
                        <l>to cheere my ſorrowing moode.</l>
                        <l>I humbly therefore pray,</l>
                        <l>with praiſes to thy name:</l>
                        <l>That he directly ſo may liue,</l>
                        <l>his deedes may merit fame.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>Powre downe thy heauenly deawe,</l>
                        <l>guard him with giftes of grace:</l>
                        <l>And triple all his former yeares,</l>
                        <l>to guide his Princely Mace.</l>
                        <l>Place truth amongſt his traine,</l>
                        <l>confound all traytrous mindes:</l>
                        <l>Amongſt the commons plant true zeale,</l>
                        <l>to doe as dutie bindes.</l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>And laſtly on my knees,</l>
                        <l>J pray my heauenly God:</l>
                        <l>From worthy <hi>Iames</hi> and from his Realme,</l>
                        <l>to ſtay his wrathfull rod.</l>
                        <l>God ſaue King <hi>Iames.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:3504:16"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
